<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Army's plea for their present practice: tendered to the consideration of all ingenuous and impartial men. Printed and published by special command.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75596</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866871</idno>
  <idno type="VID">168722</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240953661</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1000_24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207843</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866871</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866871e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75596)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168722)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E1000[24])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Army's plea for their present practice: tendered to the consideration of all ingenuous and impartial men. Printed and published by special command.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Henry Hills, printer to the Army, dwelling in Aldersgate Street next door to the Peacock.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "October. 24.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168722:1"/>
            <p>THE ARMYS PLEA FOR Their present Practice: Tendered to the consideration of all ingenuous and impartial men.</p>
            <p>Printed and published by special command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the ARMY, dwelling in <hi>Aldersgate</hi> Street next door to the <hi>Peacock.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168722:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168722:2"/>
            <head>THE Armies Plea, FOR Their present Practice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the principal end of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Government (next unto the Glory of God) is the Protection and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of all good men, in their peaceable &amp; quiet living, in all Godliness and Honesty; and that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates Duty in all Forms of Government gistrates Duty in all Forms of Government whatsoever, is to defend all men from all inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, while they so live, will doubtless be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all that consult the Oracles of God, and Principles of Reason.</p>
            <p>That the late Parliament did alwaies pretend to this great End, in all their publick Expresses, Remonstrances, Declarations, and Answers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the late King and them, will evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to all men that shall peruse the same; the very design and tendency of many whereof, was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168722:3"/> to distil into their diligent and considerate Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, an undoubted belief and perswasion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: The light of which, hath so shined into the minds and judgments of many sober and discreet men, that neither their former darkness therein, nor any subtil endeavours of deceitful Impostors, to obscure the same, will ever be able to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish that Light.</p>
            <p>That the Peoples Safety is the chief Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty; that Kings, and all that are in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, are Gods Ministers for his Peoples Good; that Governours were made for the People, and not the People for them; that they must not reign in the Peoples ruine, and be lifted up in Authority, but what (under God) they have from the People, and for their use; that uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable Power, and absolute Authority, do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come none but onely Him, whose Nature is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and can do no wrong; that though the Supreme Magistrates be above every individual, yet are they beneath, &amp; inferiour unto the whole; that they ought not to do their own wills, against the just desires of those that betrusted them; that the Powers, Honors, and Dignities of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, do respect the Peoples Interest above their own, and therefore being relatives, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies obligatory; that the essential end of all Kings, Rulers, Laws; and Governments, is the common Peace, Justice, and Safety of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; that Laws, Acts, and Statutes, are binding, or not binding, as they are evidently and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168722:3"/> relative, and conducing to common and publick Right, or Wrong; that no Governours or Governments are to be continued and tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which are directly and plainly destructive unto the chief End of their Original Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> Common Good, the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth being never obliged by any Laws (though made by their own Representatives and Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stees for making Laws) to their publick destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which is contrary to the Laws of God, Universal Reason, and Nature it self; That the Power and disposition of the publick <hi>Militia,</hi> and of the publick Treasury, were never vested by the People in their Supreme Governors, but for their Use, Peace, and Safety; That whatsoever Laws, Usage, or Customs, are against the Laws of true Religion, Reason, Nature, and Grace, are irreligious, unreasonable, unnatural, and graceless, and therefore null and void in their very making, and cannot oblige. These and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the like Principles of common reason have been distilled into the judgments and considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the free People of this Nation, by means whereof it will not be an easie matter for any Rulers in any Form of Government whatsoever, to reduce them again unto their former yoaks of bondage and slavery.</p>
            <p>From hence it is, that when those in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity shall neglect the great ends of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and improve all opportunities, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, by means of their power and gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, unto their own personal and family-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168722:4"/> especially when they shall wilfully, and against common and universal reason, act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hereunto; to the apparent danger of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon safety, they determine their Authority; and having in such cases quitted their care and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects to the peoples protection and welfare, they likewise quit the people from their allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and obedience.</p>
            <p>And as all Laws, Statutes, Acts, and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, so all Covenants, Engagements, Promises and Protestations, all acknowledgements, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptions, Vows, and Oaths, all, and all manner of obligations and expressions thereof, are only binding unto the publick safety, and not at all to the persons of the Governours, or forms of Governments, but with reference thereunto.</p>
            <p>These and the like principles of Truth and right reason, have been brought to light by the late Parliament, in their many Printed Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses, and publike Disputes, between the late King, and them, with which the apprehensions, judgements, and consciences of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands ingenuous, sober and religious persons, were occupied and instructed, and unto the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and maintenance whereof, against the said King and his Party, they devoted their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, Horses, Arms, Plate, Monies, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Children, their own persons, blood, limbs, and lives in the Service of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And upon the aforesaid principles of publick Liberty, Peace, and Safety (and nothing else
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168722:4"/> imaginable) the late Parliament did argue and pleade on behalf of themselves, and their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, their discharge from all their former prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stations, engagements, solemn Vows and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, with hands lifted up to the most high God; as also, their Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, when the King engaged himself against the publick Rights, and just Liberties of the People, and when the keeping thereof was destructive thereunto, and did also justifie many extraordinary, strange, and (doubtless in respect of the Letter of the Law) very il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal actions, <hi>viz.</hi> their taking up Arms, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing and forming Armies against the King, fighting against his Person, imprisoning, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaching, arraigning, trying, and executing him, cutting off his head, banishing his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, abolishing Bishops, Deans and Chapters, took away Kingly Government, and the House of Lords, broke the Crowns, sold the Jewels, Plate, Goods, Houses and Lands belonging un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kings of this Nation, erected extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary High Courts of Justice, and therein im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached, arraigned, condemned, and executed many notorious enemies to the publick Peace, when the Laws in being, and the ordinary Courts of Justice could not reach them; these were strange and unknown practices in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not at all justifiable (as is conceived) by any known Laws &amp; Statutes, but only by the light of the aforesaid principles of common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, justice, and equity, for the conserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168722:5"/> of the publick quiet and peace of the people.</p>
            <p>And for this cause also was the Army at first raised, formed, and commissionated, namely, for the defence of the just, civil, and religious Rights, Liberties, and Safety of the good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Nation; and not as meer Mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Hirelings to serve any Arbitrary pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er whatsoever; but were invited, and called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the late Parliament, and conjured by their severall Declarations, Remonstrances, and Expresses, printed and published in the several Market Towns, Churches, Chappels, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of publick Meetings, for the defence of themselves and the people, in the vindication and preservation of their said just Rights and Liberties, by which said publick Expresses, they have been frequently instructed, as well as by the Dictates of common reason, that it is no resistance of Magistracy to preserve the publick, natural, and undoubted Rights of the People, against those, the very nature of whose office and place of trust (as Magistrates) is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, and not to destroy the same; That the Souldiery may lawfully hold the hands of their General, that shall turn his Canon against them, and the Sea-men the hands of their Pilot, that shall apparently steer the Vessel, wherein they are, upon shelves and rocks, for the ruine of all.</p>
            <p>And as the Army was first raised for the ends aforesaid, instructed, provoked, and encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168722:5"/> by the Parliament unto the defence and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity thereof; so have they asserted the same, in fields of blood against all opposers whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and have not at all declined any hazardous attempts when they have been called thereunto; but from time to time, in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> have jeoparded their lives, in the high places of the field, against all discourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and disadvantages whatsoever, and, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting themselves and the righteousness of their cause unto the God of their Armies, have fought many bloody battels, with mighty, nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, resolute, valiant and potent Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Armies, whose numbers, strength, and several advantages (though frequently, and in many respects) did exceed theirs, yet was the Lord of hosts continually with them, and the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> their refuge, teaching their hands to war, and their fingers to fight, and covered their heads in the day of battel, giving their enemies as dust unto their sword, and as stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto their bow.</p>
            <p>And since it hath pleased God to give them the victory over their enemies, they may without vanity affirm that they have still pursued and asserted their first Cause, <hi>viz.</hi> The just Rights and Liberties of all honest and good men in their peaceable and quiet living, and not at all indulged either themselves, or others, in the troubling, suppressing or abridging any, though keen, and froward against the Army, in the free use and enjoyment of their just Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168722:6"/> yea though their zeal hath transported them, unto the most fierce, fiery, and sharpest oppositions against them, as their tongues, pens, yea and their hands also, from time to time, could possibly make against them, the charity of the Army inducing them to believe, and hope, that their intentions in the main were good, and honest, although by the subtile Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice of an ill spirited and cunning adversary, they have been seduced, and provoked frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to attempt the ruine and destruction of the Army.</p>
            <p>With what simplicity, impartiality, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightness of heart, this Army hath alwaies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted the aforesaid great end of their first e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and formation, <hi>viz.</hi> The publique peace, and quiet of all men in general, and the just Rights, and Liberties of pious people in special, though of several forms, judgements and apprehensions in some points of Religion, (if of honest and peaceable conversation) is sufficiently known, as by their constant, and uniform endeavours in this particular, against all discouragements, scandals, and reproaches, which the sharp and virulent tongues, and pens of some men could reflect upon them for the same; so also by their constant refusal to joyn, and close with any one party, or interest what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, though tempted by the most prevailing allurements of honours, profits, preferments, and incouragements, whereof the officers and souldiers could imaginablely be capable: and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168722:6"/> whether, if even at this time, they could dispense with their consciences, and accept of the wages of unrighteousness, and for their own ends and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest sakes, quit that good end and cause of their first undertaking, and fall in with some sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle interest against the rest, they might not have all the incouragements of profits and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that could be offered, or received by an Army in this kind, is tendred unto the conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all ingenuous and impartial men.</p>
            <p>But because this Army, (what ever defection hath been made by others) neither can, nor (through the implored assistance, and grace of God) ever will fall away from that good cause, which at first they undertook, and in the defence whereof, they have alwaies experienced the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence and assistance of the most High, carrying them through all difficulties and dangers, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the forces of their enemies, and making all mountains to become plains before them; the memory whereof is still fresh upon their hearts; and the praise and glory whereof, they most fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and heartily ascribe unto God; therefore it is, that all possible endeavours (that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of their adversaries could imagine, or invent) have been used to divide, break and destroy this Army, though the Lord, that knoweth their hearts, hath hitherto mercifully prevented their desired issue, causing all hands that have been stretched out, or lifted up against them, to wither, and all contrivances, plots, and projects whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to fall upon their own heads.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:168722:7"/>
            <p>Hence it hath been, that some have sharpned their pens, and whet their tongues like swords, bent their bowes, and shot out their arrows, even bitter words, scandals and reproaches against them, as if their designs were to throw down the Ministers, destroy Learning, countenance and promote all manner of errors, heresies, and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemies, depose Magistracy, and all civill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ravel all into confusion; though God, the discerner of the secret thoughts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of men, knoweth, that these are all false and scandalous, and as far from the thoughts and purposes of their hearts, as the East is from the West, and all ingenuous, and impartial men, that without prejudice have observed them, cannot but judge those charges against them to be false and frivolous. For, as for the Ministry, they have as able, and as honest ministers of their Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as they could procure, and who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Commissions from the late Parliament, for that purpose, and they could heartily wish, that they had more such among them; they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had it in their hearts to discourage, much less to destroy Learning; and they do challenge any to prove what words, or actions did ever proceed from the Army, or any considerable Members thereof, to justify such a charge against them; neither doth the Army countenance, much less promote such errors, heresies, and blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as the malicious tongues, and pens of evil minded and peevish spirited men, have sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted; though they do not judge it their duty, to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168722:7"/> discountenance well disposed, and pious men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, differing from one another in some points of Religion, whilst they demean them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in their places, as becomes them, and the known discipline of the Army; and their severe proceedings against open, and prophane swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and blasphemers, as also against known wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness amongst them, will sufficiently vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their innocency in that respect. Neither can they justly be charged to depose Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; for although they cannot in judgement and conscience permit (much less assist) Governors, to destroy the very end of civil Government it self, <hi>viz.</hi> the just interest, and rights of good men; yet did they never assume the power and exercise thereof to themselves, but left it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; some of the Army perhaps, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, being in like manner with others, called thereunto, have acted therein, there being no reason to the contrary; it is not Government, but the evils thereof, that the Army hath oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. To rectifie Governors in the administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of common right and justice, is to fasten the crowns of Government upon their heads; for although it is better to have any government then none; yet doth the Army judge it better, to alter such Governours, or Governments that seek the ruine and destruction of the very end of Government, then not to relieve the common safety of good men, to avoid the scandall of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbing such Governors or Governments in that case. Better it is to alter and remove de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168722:8"/> powers, then to permit the destruction of the people in their just rights by them.</p>
            <p>And as some have imployed their tongues and pens against this Army, to render it odious unto the people; so others have imployed their several capacities, opportunities, and advantages which they have had in the several late Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Parliaments, to break the Army in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and thereby (that still being the great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacle and block in their way) to bring about their particular designs, according to the various principles, by which they have been acted: some for one interest, others for another, and both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the interest propounded and pretended, as the main cause of the first quarrel between the late King and Parliament.</p>
            <p>As it would be too tedious to insist upon all the particular transactions (with their circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances) that (within some few years last past) have passed between those that have exercised the supreme civil powers and the Army, and the several revolutions, changes, and alterations that have fallen out thereupon; so the Army takes no pleasure to revive the memory, and mention of those things, which it were to be wished had never had their being, both in their unhappy causes, and undesireable effects, and wherein the Army do not plead a justification of all, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular act, done by them, nakedly conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without their circumstances; having been necessitated sometimes, to walk in untrodden paths in their way, as the Parliament did also in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168722:8"/> theirs. But in this particular, <hi>viz.</hi> their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant aim, and endeavor to preserve and secure the great end and cause of their first underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, <hi>viz,</hi> the just, civil, and religious rights of the good people of this Nation, in danger to be quite lost and destroyed, according to the best of their perceptions, in this their hearts do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them, and therefore have they boldness before God, and assurance of his favor, in pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their ignorances, and infirmities, and to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore his presence, direction, and assistance, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting, guiding, and blessing them in their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture undertakings.</p>
            <p>When the common adversary perceived that all their endeavors to break this Army by their friends and allyes, in the several Councils and late Parliaments, were still frustrate, and without effect (God turning all their counsels therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts into foolishness) they then betook them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves unto their Arms (not to speak of their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to engage one part of the Army against the other, a little before the dissolution of the Parliament, in the last Protectors time, and the great hopes they had thereof, by the presumed power and interest of Major General <hi>Brown,</hi> to get assistance from the City, &amp;c.) And that they might not be discovered in their intended expedition, until the prevention thereof (in all conjecturable probabilities) were altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible, they managed their design with such subtiltie and secrecy, as if they had consulted the politick wits and heads of the cunning contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168722:9"/> of the first rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> hardly suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering their left hand to know what their right hand did; insomuch that their conspiracy had reached the ears, and summoned the appearance of their great and numerous parties in all parts, Towns and Counties of the Nation; Officers commissioned, Armies concluded upon, their generals, field Officers, and Captains appointed; their particular stations and work designed; their whole party, Noble men, Knights, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Magistrates, Ministers, and commonpeople, enemies of all sorts, both the old Royalists, and others, were made acquainted therewith, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged therein; they day of their meeting through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Nation concluded upon, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most at hand before the discovery thereof; the success whereof on the adversaries side was so probable, and promising, as that they feared not to issue out at last their declarations and expresses in print, inviting the people to joyn with them; their confidence thereupon was so great, as that they spake much after the rate of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the Egyptians, upon their march after Israel, when they thought they could not escape, We will pursue, we will overtake, we will divide the spoil, our lust shall be satisfied upon them, we will draw our swords, and our hand shall destroy them.</p>
            <p>But it pleased the Lord, out of his accustomed mercy and goodness, by small parties of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in several Counties and Cities, to prevent
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168722:9"/> the gathering together of the Enemy in most places, onely in and about <hi>Chester,</hi> a great party of them, Horse and Foot, in good equipage, were met together, formed themselves into a considerable Army, who were indeed like a black and thick cloud, that threatned to vent it self in dismal storms of fire and blood upon the Parliament, against whom they manifested their keenest resolutions, as also against all those that still adhered unto their first Principles, and that <hi>Old Cause</hi> wherein they at first ingaged with the Parliament against the late King.</p>
            <p>Upon which it pleased the Parliament to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Lord <hi>Lambert</hi> with a Brigade to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press the said Enemy, who with much readiness of mind, chearfulness and resolution, did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake that Service, and marched away with all possible expedition; who (through the blessing of God) managed that Affair with such Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Courage, and Resolution, as that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy was totally routed, dispersed, and suppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, with very little loss of blood; his indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours being, as much as could be, to prevent the shedding of blood.</p>
            <p>The Officers of the same Brigade, being full of the sense of that seasonable Mercy and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, considered how they might improve the same unto the Glory of God, and good of the Nation; and withal, calling to mind how craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily their Adversaries and their Abettors in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, by fair speeches and feigned words, pretences and suggestions, deceived them, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168722:10"/> the rest of the good People of the Nation, of the benefit of such Successes and Victories; and finding the Peoples disaffection to be more general than was conceived by the Parliament, did agree upon an humble Petition and Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals unto the Parliament, and together with a very sober and Christian Letter, sent the said Petition and Proposals unto the Lord <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> with a desire that (if he thought fit) it might be communicated to a General Council of Officers, for their approbation.</p>
            <p>His Lordship forthwith communicated the said Letter and Paper to Sir <hi>Arthur Hesilrig,</hi> with a desire that himself, Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> and Major <hi>Salwey,</hi> would give his Lordship a meeting, to consider what was fit to be done therein. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead thereof, the next day Sir <hi>Arthur Hesilrig</hi> (upon what account is unknown) acquainted the House with the said Paper, and that there was a dangerous design among some in the Army, &amp;c. upon which rumours were spread abroad of new attempts to introduce a Government by a single person again; which was directly contrary to the very scope and design of the said Paper. Whereupon the House presently ordered an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to be given to the Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, reproachfull speeches were cast up and down, of sending the Lord <hi>Lambert</hi> to the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; that some of the Chief Officers of the said Brigade deserved to be hanged, drawn, and quartered, with many the like keen and angry reflections: by all which it did appear to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168722:10"/> my, that there was a design either to divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Parliament and the Army, or between the Army and the good People of the Nation, or to make divisions and contrary parties in the Army it self. Whereupon, the Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that were in Town, being between two and three hundred, met together, and agreed upon an humble Representation and Petition, which was delivered to the Parliament, and they had the thanks of the House for the same, with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise that their Proposals in the said Petition should be taken into Consideration, all which have been printed and published.</p>
            <p>At the said General Council of Officers (that nothing might be done by them that were in Power, but that the rest of the Officers that were absent, and equally concerned, should have the cognizance thereof, Directions were given for sending the said Representation and Petition inclosed in a Letter to their respective Regiments and Garisons, one of which Letters being sent to Colonel <hi>Okey</hi>'s Regiment, was brought unto the House by a Member thereof; upon reading of which, the House immediately declared the Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi>'s Commission void, together with the Commission of the Lord <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> General <hi>Disbrow,</hi> and of six Colonels and one Major: and all this, without so much as causing them to come before them, and hearing them speak one word for themselves, or exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whether the Names subscribed therein, were the hand-writings of the said Officers;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168722:11"/> and all arising from that very matter, for which the Army had the thanks of the House but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before.</p>
            <p>And not only so, but things were so contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that a Regiment commanded by Colonel <hi>Morley</hi> (who with six others were appointed to command the Army) was brought for a guard to the House, several Barrels of Powder laid in, together with provision of victuals, in order to the effectual carrying on of some designe.</p>
            <p>The Officers of the Army having knowledge of these things, and perceiving such strange and violent courses and proceedings against some of the chief of them, without any just cause, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and trial, considering and expecting that it would be their own cases the next day, they being all alike concerned in the same thing: the said Officers so put out, having done nothing for which they were so censured but by their order; And observing further the zeal of many in the House for the punishment of those, for no just cause, who (but as yesterday) ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured their lives to suppress a potent and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Enemy in the field, and how cold and backward they were unto the trial and punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the said Enemy whom they subdued; and clearly perceiving a resolution either totally to destroy, or quite change and alter the very spirit and temper of this Army, and to form an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other for their own ends and purposes: And lastly, discerning that by such proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, as aforesaid, in turning them out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168722:11"/> of their Commands and Trust for no just cause at all, and that they must neither present inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Petitions to them, nor write innocent Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to one another, for the promotion of things honest, just and meet, worthy of their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance and thanks: The Army (perceicing these things) had little hopes that the publike Liberties and Interest of this Nation, and the people of God therein, could be long freed from violation and utter destruction, and therefore, they did put a stop unto the sitting of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, concluding it betraying of that trust and Cause (for which they were first raised) which is more precious unto them then their lives, should they neglect their present oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to preserve the same. With what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses, intentions, and resolutions the Army did invite the Parliament to sit again, after their long suspension from their sitting; What hopes they had of their doing great and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things for the happy settlement of this poor, harrased, and distracted Nation; With what promises and assurances from many princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Members of them, these hopes and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations of the Army were begotten, fed, and nourished, are known unto God that judgeth right: But how these things have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the settlement of the Nation endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured and hastened, how much can be done (if they be pleased) even in one day, against their faithful friends, and how little, in six
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168722:12"/> moneths for the common and publick good, is to apparent. The resolution as likewise the practice of the Parliament, to give all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions themselves unto the Officers of the Army, from the highest to the lowest, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the publike Revenues of Customes and Excise but for three moneths, the delay in their Act of Assessements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were not without the observation and jealousies of some, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe hereof was their own continuance and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity, creating a necessity thereunto, or the making void the power and maintenance of the Army. And the inward did-favour, if not (since their sitting, though covertly carried) purposes of revenge against the Army, was more then conjecturable, by their backwardness to set out the Act of Indemnity; Notwithstanding which Act, they passed a Vote against Major General <hi>Harrison,</hi> making him uncapable of future pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick employment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for no new or other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but his joyning with other Officers of the Army in the interruption of the Parliament, which the Army could not but judge to be against all Rules of Equity, and Justice, and a precedent, threatning all the rest of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers that had a hand in the said interruption, to fare alike, upon the first opportunity of politick conveniency thereunto; for that Act did either pardon him, or not; if it did pardon him, then that sentence against him was unrighteous and unjust, because against the publick faith of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168722:12"/> Parliament declared in their own Act, printed and published by their command, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly hath been the greatest security that the people of <hi>England</hi> could have for any thing: If it did not pardon him, neither did it then pardon any of the Army that had a hand in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said interruption, and so it signified nothing at all; If the penning that Act was with such care, caution, and implicite Liberty left in the House, to punish any man that had a hand int he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said interruption, then did they only seem to pardon whom they did intend to punish, and so that Act was a meer collusion, and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting with that simplicity and uprightness of minde, and good affection to the Army which was pretended thereby, nor yet to that sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of love to them wherewith the Army did close and joyn with them; nor indeed answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that plainness of expression as might challenge the confidence and belief of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in future times to depend upon the security even of an Act of Parliament: And lastly, their apt, forward, and severe proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the chief of their Army, without any just cause given hereunto, and indeed straining and catching at an occasion of offence when not given, do not a little argue more then a tincture of secret discontents and purposes to reckon with them for their foresaid interruption.</p>
            <p>The Army is not insensible of the many an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and impertinent reflections like to be cast upon them for this Act, by the petulancy and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168722:13"/> frowardness of some discontented and inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate persons, whose self same tongues can, and frequently do, both bless and curse, commend and condemn the self fame actions (at several times performed) as their own interests are like to stand or fall thereby: Neither are they much sollicitous or careful about that matter, being sufficiently furnished with satisfactory rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in their own consciences, to cut the sinews of any material Objection that can be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them.</p>
            <p>They are not likewise willing to enter into the controversie and debate of all that may be said with reference to the Parliament, for or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their Parliamentary authority, and the indissolvableness of them without their own consent, nor are they altogether ignorant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; That which did encourage the Army to invite them to sit again, was the consideration and remembrance of what great things God did do by them, their many years knowledge and experience which they had of the complexion, temper, and state of the Commonwealth, and their presumed abilities and disposition to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour and bring about a safe and happy settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, to the great contentment of the people, and equitable satisfaction of all honest interests, and the many hopeful promises and assurances that were given thereof: And the Army was resolved to adhere unto them to the utmost of their power to assist them therein, and did therefore judge it their duty to invite them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168722:13"/> to sit; but alas, their hopes herein, hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like smoak: they looked for peace, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> behold a rent, and for a time of healing, but no good came.</p>
            <p>If this Army, and the continuance thereof be necessary to preserve that first just Cause, for the preservation whereof they were first raised (there being scarce any thing obstructions unto the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of it, but the Army) it was then necessary for them to take that course which they have done; for who seeth not, that if so be three of their Chief Officers, and seven Field Officers, can be puft away with a breath, for no cause gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, without hearing, examination, trial, or proof made of any fault committed, and the rest of the Officers remaining every whit as much in the pretended offence as they, and therefore as much obnoxious to be destroyed (in respect of their standing in the Army) by the breath of their nostrils, as their Superiours and Brethren were; (the case being so) who seeth not, but that the Army now must take its leave and last farewell of their old friends, and that Cause which they have maintained hitherto with good success (through Gods blessing) or take up new resolutions to try yet what possibly may be done for the conservation thereof, and not to deliver up that Sword out of their hands, for the smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of that Cause, which God by his Providence did put into their hands for its Protection and Defence.</p>
            <p>It is not denied but the Officers of the Army
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168722:14"/> did promise and engage to be true, faithfull, and constant unto the Parliament, which they did with all uprightness and singleness of heart: and so did the Parliament when time was, in the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn league and Covenant, in a most serious manner, with hands lifted up unto the most high God, to defend the Kings person, honour, and dignity, in the preservation of our Liberties and Religion, &amp;c. and yet afterward did arraign, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, and execute him; and yet doubtless do believe that they have not broken their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant notwithstanding. In like manner, the Officers of the Army did engage to be true, faithfull, and constant to the Parliament; but though the Parliament was not pleased to insert the Condition of that Engagement, <hi>viz.</hi> in the maintenance of that Old Cause, the preservati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the just rights and liberties of all the pious and good people of the nation, living a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and quiet life in all godliness and honesty, yet must it be implied and understood: for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that condition was intended, or not; if not, then was it unlawful, and so null and void in its very making; and as the making of such an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conditionate engagement and promise, is sin; so the keeping thereof is sin also, and so an adding of sin unto sin. If it were intended, though not exprest, then the Army hath not broken their Covenant with the Parliament, because their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry judgements and consciences (upon arguments very convincing unto them, are satisfied, that (if this Army were out of the way, whereunto those
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168722:14"/> Votes of cashiering the chief Officers thereof were praevious) they are perswaded upon grounds and reasons too enforcing, that all the pious and good people of this Nation, should not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a peaceable and quiet life in all godliness and honesty, but only some part of them; and that many thousands of good people in this Land, that differ in judgement and practice in some points of religion, and forms of worship from others, should be enforced either to sin in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity against their consciences, or again, as in times of old, to seek their spirituall food, yea, and bodily also, in desolate places, or else submit themselves unto the intolerable yoak of perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and fiery trials. And what is this, but to give up that Cause which for so many years hath, by Gods blessing, been asserted and maintained with good success, though with the loss of so much treasure and blood, that hath been expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereabout?</p>
            <p>Again, the fore-mentioned Votes, discharging the said Officers from their places of command in the Army, were for something, or for nothing; if for nothing, then were they meerly arbitrary, unreasonable, and unrighteous; yea, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Parliaments promise to them, that the Officers of the Army from time to time, should receive marks of the favor of the Parliament, and countenance answerable to their faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and merit; which faithfulness and merit doth respect either the time past, or to come; if the time past, and with an eye to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168722:15"/> act of interruption, and leavin a liberty in them, to punish them for the same, intending rather their presumed unfaithfulness and deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, then their faithfulness and merit, then that vote was no promise, but a threatning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the vizard of a promise, and so still a very collusion.</p>
            <p>If it did respect the time to come, then that Promise hath not been kept, except cashiering be a mark of favour.</p>
            <p>Again, if their foresaid cashiering was not an arbitrary act of meer will and pleasure, but for just cause; what then was that cause? Why were they not called to an account, and heard before sentenced? which in all equity (especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally their former gracious promise of marks of favour considered) should have been done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If it be said, That the Parliament thought it convenient for publick good to take away the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions of those Officers, which they gave unto them of their free pleasure; and that they are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e else are the proper Judges of what is convenient to be done for common Interest in that case: and that the said Officers ought to have submitted thereunto:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Answer; If it be granted, That the being of this Army, and the continuance also in the vigorous sence of their first just principles and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution to protect all good men of honest and paceable lives and conversation, in their civil and religious Liberties, be absolutely necessary (which cannot reasonably be denied) then common and apparent reason must be the only judge.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:168722:15"/>
            <p>The Army grants, That in doubtful and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable Cases, the Parliament is the onely Judge, and all must submit: but if the Parliament judge, and say that noon-day is midnight, or if they Vote that it is Liberty, and not Bondage, to be tyed in chains, and cast into dungeons, and there kept, must men submit in that case? Suppose the Parliament should make their peace with the Scotch King, upon condition of security of their Lives, Liberties and Estates to themselves, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and posterity, and for quietness sake, for the settlement of the Nation, should resolve to Enact, That all men whatsoever shall submit and conform themselves in their judgements and practice, unto what doctrines, discipline and worship the said King and a free Parliament (to be hereafter chosen by his Writs) shall Enact, must the Army and all others quietly submit, and lay down their heads upon blocks to be cut off without asking any question for conscience sake? whatever is the opinion of the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in this point now; it is most certain, that was not their opinion in 1648. the sum then of this is, That as the late Parliament in one of their Declarations spake of their treating with the late King, <hi>viz. A declaration of the Lords and Commons of the</hi> 4th. <hi>of</hi> March, 1647. <hi>in answer to the Papers of the Scotch Commissioners;</hi> so may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Army say of their submission to these Votes, <hi>viz.</hi> that they cannot suffer themselves to be Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of all that they have fought for, nor that under the pretence of publick good, Voted so
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168722:16"/> to be by the Parliament, for the satisfying of all Interests, one Interest should be set up, which should devour all the rest. Surely if this must be the issue of all, after so much expence of the Treasure and blood of the Nation: The Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament and Army should have taken this into consideration, before they had engaged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves and the Nation in so much Cost and Blood, which was not onely spent unnecessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but also very unlawfully. Who doth not see that this will bring upon them all the blood that hath been shed in this War? neither do they think they ought to suffer themselves to be Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted first out of their Commands in the Army, and next unto the Gallows, with all their friends and Party, for nothing, but their adhering unto that first just Cause, whereunto they are Invited, conjured, and sworn so to adhere with their lives and Fortunes, even by them that so vote them.</p>
            <p>Again, by the Parliament must be meant the major part of the Parliament, and not the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor: and if so, it cannot be forgotten, that these very Gentlemen of Parliament, when they were a minor Party in the House, and could not carry on that great Cause of publick Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which at first they asserted, being overpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the contrary Party in the House, through the defection that many of them made from the same, that then they did rest satisfied in permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Army to be Judge in the Case, and (not to say, did invite and desire them to take away several of the leading Party of the said dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168722:16"/> Members) did acquiesce and rest satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the reasons given by the Army for their so Acting; the very spirit and life of which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons did consist in this, that they could not in conscience permit them, (that is, the major part of the House, for a minor part could not) to destroy the Cause, which they (by commands of Parliament, and in conscience of the Vows and Covenants imposed upon them by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) did undertake, when they were first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited into Arms. And if they might be Judge of what was meet to be done to secure the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cause of the good people of the Nation; then why may they not (the case being the same in their very judgements and consciences) be Judges of what is necessary for them to do now also?</p>
            <p>For conclusion, The Army desire all sober and judicious men, to stop their ears against all uncharitable jealousies, and unreasonable suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, which rancorous and evil-minded men may suggest against them, and to assure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, that all pious and just Magistrates, all godly, able, and peaceable Ministers, all honest, quiet, and sober-minded Christians, all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Commonwealth, shall find the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, according to their utmost abilities, ready to secure and defend them in their Persons, Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions, just Rights, and Interests, against all persons whatsoever, that shall offer violence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; that through the implored blessing and assistance of the onely wise God, who bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168722:17"/> light out of darkness, and good out of evil, such foundations of Government and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Settlement will be now laid, after these late Revolutions and Changes: as also such a firm Union (not onely in the Army amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, who have now resolved and engaged, that they will never unadvisedly be seduced to divide into parties against one another, but also) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Army and all queit and peaceable people of the Land, as shall for ever henceforth break the hearts and hopes of all those adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, forraign and domestick, that wait for their confusion by their divisions, that Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Charity, Justice, Truth and Peace, and the blessed Gospel of Jesus Christ may altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther run, and be glorified.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>